A Guide to the Duncan A. MacInnes papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA178
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Subject files, 4 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence (Box 8)
    - National Science Foundation, 1952-1955 1957-1963
      1952-1955 Recommendations on grants. 1957-1963 correspondence and budget dealing with NSF-C5093 and GP-1956.
    - Reprint requests, 1945-1946
    - Vosmoy Club, 1945-1946
  - Conferences arranged chronologically, 1953 (Box 9)
    Includes correspondence dealing with details of arrangements with participants, preparations and some final reports. After 1953 consist mostly of letters from chairman of particular conference clearing through Dr. MacInnes.
    Conferences. In 1945 Dr. MacInnes, dissatisfied with results of conferences attended by large numbers, suggested to Dr. Jewett and Dr. Bronk that the National Academy of Sciences sponsor and support specialized 3-day conferences limited to no more than 25 participants actively at work in the particular subject area.
    They were held primarily at Ram's Head Inn on Shelter Island and Arden House, though the first was held at The Rockefeller Institute.
    - Bioelectric Potentials Conference 1946 Dec. 13-14. Papers in honor of W.J.V. Osterhout under auspices of National Academy of Sciences at RIMR. Papers by Kenneth S. Cole, L.R. Blinks, Rafael Lorente de No, 1946 December 13-14
    - Bioelectric Potentials Conference, 1946-1947
      Correspondence on arrangements, expenses and evaluation. Dated 1947 Nov. 7 a copy of MacInnes report on 1946 Conference and June 1947 Conference.
    - Bioelectric Potentials Conference. Correspondence on publication of conference material including summaries and figures. Holograph letters from L.R. Blinks
    - Quantum Mechanics Conference 1947 June 2-4 held at Ram's Head Inn. Correspondence
    - Low Temperature Conference 1948 May 31, June 1-2 held at Ram's Head Inn. Correspondence, 1948 June 1-2
    - Gene Conference, 1949 May 30-June 2
    - Ultracentrifuge Conference, 1949 June 14-16
    - Statistical Mechanics Conference, 1950 June 6-8
    - Quantum Mechanical Methods in Valence Theory Conference, 1951 September 8-10
    - Mechanism of Hormone Action Conference with special reference to the adrenal cortex 1952 Jan 17-19 held at Arden House, 1952 January 17-19
    - Partial Differential Equations Conference held at Arden House, 1952 October 9-11
    - Biochemistry, Paleocology and Evolution Conference 1953 June 9-11 at Ram's Head Inn
    - Operator Theory and Group Representations Conference, 1953 October 20-23
    - Linear Algebras Conference, 1956 June 6-8
    - Mathematics of Quantum Theory Conference, 1958 June 3-6
  - Annual reports, lectures, addresses and manuscripts (Box 10)
  - Annual reports to Scientific Directors, 1927-1956 1959 (Box 10)
    (duplicated copies).
  - War Research report to Scientific Directors with illustrations, 1942-1945 (Box 10)
    Undated but work done 1942-45.
  - Lecture: The glass electrode (Box 10)
    (2 cop. one with list of slides).
    - American Chemical Society, 1933 November 20
    - Brown University, 1934 October 11
    - University of Illinois, 1936 May 5
  - Lecture: Arhennius and Debye Huckel Theory, undated (Box 10)
  - Lecture: The Interionic attraction Theory of Electrolytes Undated (Box 10)
    Includes list of slides.
  - Lists of slides used for lectures (Box 10)
    - Electrophoresis
      - Washington, DC, 1942 April 9
      - Amherst, Mass, 1942 November 16
    - Effect of centrifugal force on electromotive force of galvanic cell
      - American Physical Society, 1943 October 23
      - Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute, 1943 October 28
    - Study of proteins by electrophoresis
      - Sigma Xi, New Haven, 1945 March 9
      - American Chemical Society, New York, 1944 September 12
    - Transference numbers and Debye Huckel theory
      - Cornell University, 1945 May
    - Study of proteins by electrophoresis
      - Cornell University, 1945 May
    - Effect of centrifugal force on the potentials of galvanic cells
      - Cornell University, 1945 May
  - Manuscripts, undated (Box 10)
    - "Some suggestions concerning the pedagogy of research"
    - "[Creative evolution] "
  - Lecture: Nichols Medal Address, 1942 "Galvanic Cells as Instruments of Research" (Box 10)
  - Priestly lectures, Pennsylvania State College, 1943 March 22-26 (Box 10)
    Includes program, slide list and correspondence.
  - Phi Beta Kappa/Sigma Xi lectures 1946 Apr. 1 at Rutgers University, 1946 April 1 (Box 10)
    Includes correspondence and handwritten notes of lecture.
  - Acheson Medal Address 1948 October 14 (Box 10)
    Includes presentation address by R.M. Burns and Chemical and Engineering News cover and article (photocopy).
  - Presentation address: 1948 Hillebrand Prize to Edgar Reynolds Smith (Box 10)
  - American Chemical Society lecture tour, 1949 October 1-8 (Box 10)
    Correspondence on arrangements.
  - L'Institut de Chimie du Canada, 1950 November 23-23 (Box 10)
    Correspondence on arrangements, abstract and program.
  - Presentation address of 1954 Nichols Medal to Charles Phelps Smyth (Box 10)
  - Abstract of Edgar R. Smith Ph.D. thesis at M.I.T., 1921-1923 (Box 10)
  - "A Study of the Glass Electrode" by D.A. MacInnes and Laurie L. Burgess (Box 10)
    Includes drawings. Undated.
  - "The Glass Electrode Method for Measuring ph Values" Corrected copy for chapter in Donald Van Slyke book, 1941 (Box 10)
  - "The Electromotive Force Centrifuge Factors affecting Precision" by Robert L. Kay and D.A. MacInnes. Carbon copy with illustrations, Published 1957 (Box 10)
  - "Activity Coefficients from the Potentials of Concentration Cells" Letter to editors of Nature, undated (Box 10)
  - "The Principles of Electrochemistry", 100 revised pages (Box 10)
  - Figures and photographs used in publications (Box 11)
    Miscellaneous (contents list in folder).
  - Activity coefficients (Box 11)
  - Conductance (Box 11)
  - Electrophoresis (Box 11)
  - Emf centrifuge (with Dayhoff and Ray) (Box 11)
  - pH glass electrode (Box 11)
  - Potentiometric titrations; oxidation reduction potentials (Box 11)
  - Transference (Box 11)
  - Unidentified (Box 11)
- Photographs, 5
  Photographs taken by Dr. MacInnes. Mostly unidentified but also includes 3 albums: one a family record and 2 of camping trips.
  - Photographs by Dr. MacInnes (Box 12)
    - Western trips
    - European trip
    - Gaspe, Perce
    - Vermont
    - unidentified, 2 folders
  - Photographs by Dr. MacInnes and others
    - New York scenes (Box 13)
    - Family and colleagues (Box 13)
    - unidentified people, One album (Box 13)
      Family record
    - snapshots of trips, 2 albums (Box 13)
    - photographs by Dr. MacInnes (Box 14)
    - unidentified, mounted (Box 14)
- Map collection, 6
  Maps of climbing and camping areas. Many are topographic maps.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to the nature and potentially brittle condition of the contents of the map collection, special arrangements may be required in order to view materials. Individual items may be restricted due to preservation concerns.
  - Map collection (Box 15)
    - A
      Atlantic Coast. Primarily New York City and State and Ocean.
    - B-C
      Balkans; Black Rock Forest (N.Y. State).
      Canadian-Pacific Railroad.
      Canadian Rockies.
      Chamonix.
      Colorado.
      Crater Lake.
    - D-G
      Dauphiné-Savoie.
      England.
      France.
      Glacier Park.
      Grand Canyon.
      Grand Tetons.
    - I-M
      India.
      Italy.
      Katahdin.
      Lac St. Jean.
      London.
      Manhattan.
      Marcy.
      Massachusetts.
      Mexico.
      Monadnock.
      Moscow.
      Mt. Desert.
      Mt. Mansfield.
      Mt. Rainier.
      Mt. Washington.
    - N-R
      New England.
      New York State.
      Paris.
      Pennsylvania.
      Placid.
      Pound Ridge.
      Quebec.
      Rainy Lake.
      Rocky Mt. National Park.
    - S-V
      Scotland.
      Seattle.
      South America.
      Soviet Union.
      Switzerland.
      Vermont.
    - W-Z
      White Mountains.
      Wisconsin.
      World map.
      Wyoming.
      Yosemite.
      Zermatt.
- War contract work, 1941-1945; 7
  In 1940 Dr. Vannevar Bush was authorized to form the National Defense Research Committee which in 1941 was absorbed by the Office of Scientific Research and Development. Under the direction of Dr. Bush, Dr. Conant of Harvard was in charge of the research done on chemistry and explosives. Problems were farmed out on contract to universities and other existing installations. Two such contracts, OEMsr-130 and OEMsr-350 were arranged with The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research with Duncan MacInnes as the senior investigator. On the OEMsr-130 contract much of the laboratory work was under the supervision of Donald Belcher.
  - War contract OEMsr-130 (Box 16)
    - Arrangements. Correspondence, 1941 February-1945 June
      Correspondents include:.
      Bush, Vannevar.
      Byfield, Abbott.
      Chadwell, Harris M.
      Feiser, Louis F.
      Johnson, Warren C.
      MacRae, Duncan.
      Sherwood, T.K.
    - Apparatus, 1941 July-1942 October
    - Program, 1940 September-1943 July
    - Materials, 1941 December-1945 April
    - Property-accounting. Disposal of HS, 1945 April-1946 [July?]
    - Personnel. General correspondence, 1941 July-1945 May
    - Personnel
      Alphabetical by name of assistant.
      Belcher, Donald.
      Belove, Louis.
      Best, Robert.
      Bodner, Harry.
      Borstelmann, Joseph.
      Bradshaw, Benjamin C.
      Bundy, W.S.
      Gand, Rudolph.
      Jacknowski, Joseph.
      Longsworth, L.G.
      Shedlovsky, T.
      Sohmer, Martha.
      Tait, Andrew.
    - Reports, 1941-1945
      Mainly correspondence about work done in other installations and brief reports of work done at RIMR transmitted in letter form, primarily by Donald Belcher.
      Includes memoranda on Edgewood Spray Tests (DuPont Co.) July/Aug. 1943.
    - Meetings, 1941-1944
      Includes correspondence and minutes.
    - Travel. Vouchers and reimbursement records for travel on war contract, 1940-1945
      Includes some correspondence.
  - War contract OEMsr-130 (Box 17)
    - Belcher, Donald. Correspondence., 1941-1945
      - Byfield, Abbott
        Highlighted correspondent.
      - McRae, Duncan
      - Sherwood, T.K.
    - Belcher, Donald, 1940-1944
      Correspondence Edgewood Arsenal 1943 correspondence with Texas Oil Company.
    - Reports on War Contract
      - Correspondence, 1941 July-1945 September
      - Report receipts including final, formal and monthly, 1942-1943 1944-1945
    - Office file. Report receipts
      - 1941-1942
      - 1943
      - 1944-1945
  - War contract OEMsr-350 (Box 18)
    - Vesicant abstracts including index
    - War Department TM 1-282. "Tactics and Techniques of Air Chemical Spraying"
    - Correspondence in one chronological file dealing with budget, contract arrangements, personnel, property accounting, meetings and travel
      Stewart, Irvin.
      Urey, Harold C.
    - Contract, formal, 1946-1947
      Office file of report receipts; final disposition including correspondence on declassification and photocopy of two declassified reports.
    - Correspondence on patent, 1944-1945
    - Correspondence on security clearance
      Including requests for deferment from army service and includes fingerprints.
      Best, Robert J.
      Kobelt, Nina.
      Longsworth, Lewis G.
      MacInnes, Duncan A.
      Taub, David.
      Wyckoff, Irene E.
    - Charge sheets for equipment and supplies, 1941-1945
    - Special stamps
      Signature D-Acct.
      Signature F-Acct.
      Confidential.
      Secret.
  - File of government communications and directives as maintained in Duncan MacInnes department (Box 19)
    Arranged under index as follows.
    1:00 Activities of NDRC
    2:00 Activities of OSRD
    3:00 Activities of CMR (Alien property custodian)
    4:00 Classified information documents or materials (see also Mail)
    5:00 Contracts
    6:00 Liaison office of the OSRD
    7:00 Mail
    8:00 Meetings (nothing found here)
    9:00 Navy Department
    10:00 Patents
    11:00 Personnel-appointments
    12:00 Personnel-clearance
    13:00 Personnel-general
    14:00 Personnel-identification
    15:00 Priority ratings
    16:00 Procedure-inter-office (see Mail)
    17:00 Procedure-intra-office
    18:00 Progress reports
    19:00 Supplies (nothing found here)
    20:00 Telegraph (nothing found here)
    21:00 Telephones
    22:00 Travel regulations
    23:00 Visits to government departments or plants working on NDRC defense contracts
    24:00 War Department
    25:00 Equipment-office (nothing found here)
    26:00 Equipment-miscellaneous (nothing found here)
- Guest book from FL. Montgomery Cottage, 1953-1972 (Package envelope)
- Administrative correspondence and miscellaneous, 2½"
  Immediate Source of Acquisition note
  File from Office of Faculty and Student Records received 10 February 1983.
  - Administrative correspondence, 1926-1935 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Administrative correspondence, 1936-1945 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Administrative correspondence, 1946-1959 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Administrative correspondence, 1961-1966 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1942-1948 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    Includes newspaper and magazine clippings re Nichols Medal 1942, and Acheson Medal 1948 (Feature article in "Chemical and Engineering News" 25 Oct 1948; Holograph notes by Detlev W. Bronk for MacInnes Memorial Service.
- "Collected Reprints", 2 bound volumes